Pope Francis used that term. He says
this is an exciting technology but also
a fearsome technology. So it's okay to
have that fear but that that fear
sometimes comes from ignorance. So if we
can defeat ignorance then we have a
chance to move from from something that
could be potentially harmful to
something that could be really harness
for good.
Ed Mundo and Edmund, it's a it's a real
pleasure to have the opportunity to
speak with both of you today. Um, just
kind of starting out, I know that both
of you come from strong uh ministry
backgrounds. Edmund, I know that you you
worked in parish ministry for for quite
a while. Edmundo, I I know on the diosis
level in Detroit, you you worked in in
communications. Um, if you guys could
share for our audience who might not
know so much about you guys. Um, how did
those experiences shape how you see
technologies role in the church today?
And maybe Edmundo, we can start with
you.
Well, thank you so much, Benjamin. I'm
so happy to be here and uh with Edmund
as well. Um he's a close collaborator
and a friend and um yeah, we're happy to
be here. Uh yeah, that's a great
question. So, I I um I was in college
during the digital revolution, the first
one. So, um I got to witness firsthand
the excitement around uh technologies.
We would call them emerging technologies
at that time. And um in in fact I was
studying economics and I switched to
communications because of the excitement
um that I had with these new
technologies and and it just sounds
funny now when you say new technologies
emerging technologies and you're
referring to the internet and email but
it was it was like mind-blowing. It was
it was the time where um yeah just
things were changing and very very
quickly. Um so so at that time I was 17
years old. I switched I had a powerful
encounter with the Lord. I went to this
retreat and had a very very powerful
encounter with the Lord and um and I
felt called to be at the intersection of
technology and media and evangelization
from the very very beginning. So that's
been always part of who I am and what I
do uh with my career and I've been very
blessed to to be able to to serve the
Lord in that intersection. Um so um at
that time again I was young I was I was
looking at all these technologies and
and one of the things that I was always
so it it was always so encouraging to me
was the approach of the church um that
it was never um it was always um
providing wisdom on how to navigate this
changing world. Um but it was always
very hopeful. It was about how can we
use these technologies to advance the
mission of Christ in the world. And and
that was a type of framework that was
reinforced in me at a very early age of
always thinking about technologies and
emerging technologies and media um as a
tool that we can harness for good and
for the mission of the church. There are
obviously um things that we need to be
careful about and we need to use our
discernment. But that was always the the
voice of the church from the very very
beginning. we're talking about mid '90s
and it continued until now um with
different things that that that the
popes and the magisterium are are you
know the church magisterium is teaching
us on how to navigate these and how to
be careful about it. So um but it's
always been like that. It's always been
in my heart the desire to leverage
technology and media to evangelize. Um
at the heart of it is you know the
gospel is a story. It's the best story
that can be told. Uh the best story that
has ever been told and can be told. Um,
and I always wanted to to use media and
leverage media to tell that story to the
world.
>> Edmund, if if you could share a little
bit about about your background and how
your experience working in parish
ministry has has informed how you see
technology uh being utilized and
harnessed by the church.
>> Yeah, I I had 10 years in parish
ministry experience and I started out as
a youth minister. So, um, for me that
meant having a pretty pretty tight
budget and having to to do a lot of to
wear a lot of different hats. So, um,
when you're in that situation and you're
kind of, um, brave enough to experiment
with different, um, tech or software
tools and things like that, um, that was
definitely something I I I did. And so I
think it shaped me by um on the one hand
like teaching me how to be yeah I guess
scrappy and and test things but I think
it also um showed me that you know the
technologies like if I'm working on
something the night before and then I'm
in front of people the next day it's
very quick to figure out like what works
and what doesn't with with people you
know and so I think it helped me always
place like the person at the center of
any technology or thing you know
software or app that we were
um if it's not going to be helpful for
ministry to other people then um yeah it
just gets thrown out really quickly. So
I think those two things there was a lot
of testing experimenting and then um
just seeing what worked and what didn't
and I think I still kind of have that
mentality with the different tech and
tools that I use today. What can what
can you share about your experience, you
know, in parish ministry and working,
you know, with with young adults, with
with with adults and of course, you
know, with with younger people, like has
technology become something central to
almost every interaction or are there
certain core interactions, core aspects
of that ministry that that even if we'd
like to offload it to technological, you
know, efficiency or whatever, like it it
is centered around the PE people and
that community.
>> Yeah. I mean, the the technology, I
mean, it's it's uh what is it? There's
the Marshall McClean quote about, you
know, fish didn't discover water like
that. Like like it it's just such a part
of our culture that even if you have
teens or parishioners who aren't
actively power users of technology, the
whole culture is is or has been impacted
by technology and these tools and these
these inventions. So um yeah, it was a
part of everything and and I'm I'm sure
both of you have heard so many stories
of different parishes or ministries or
even ministers who um kind of, you know,
looked back lovingly on the days before
all of these technological inventions
and then they kind of got left behind in
the sense that it was really hard to
communicate. It it was hard to relate to
people who this is part of their whole
world. Um, you know, they might be with
the church one or two hours a week and
then all the other hours are spent in a
in a culture in a society just I mean
technology isn't just a part of that
society. It it like is society like it's
it's such a a core part of the fabric of
what we experience day-to-day.
>> Um, and then Edmundo may maybe to to
jump to you. Um, you know, the late Pope
Benedict the 16th spoke about the
digital continent and the need to
evangelize that that continent and Pope
Francis of course spoke a lot about um
about evangelizing online, you know,
using even the word the term digital
continent. Um, where do you think we are
as a church? Are we are we pioneers on
the digital continent? Are we settlers?
Are we still tourists? Um, what what's
your gauge on that?
>> Yeah, it's a great question. Um, I love
that um phrase from Pope Benedict
because it helps us think in missionary
terms, right? Uh, in our duty to carry a
message, a message of hope, a message of
of of life, right, into a place. Um,
interestingly, the the church has
evolved in the way that they talk about
uh digital in general. Um, with with
Pope Benedict, um, we got that that
phrase of the digital content. Again, I
think it's very helpful in in in many
ways and I love it so much. Um, but you
see a change with from then to Pope
Francis and now with with Pope Leo where
the church understands it a little bit
different and more along the lines of
what Edund was saying. Uh, they use the
digital culture instead of digital
content more uh now um in in church
documents. Um, so it it kind of makes
sense if you think of it. um Pope
Benedict um and and that generation I'm
part of that generation too even JP2 we
were immigrants right coming into these
digital continents right we were we were
it wasn't something that we grew up with
but we had to learn how to be in it um
and then you have millennials and and
younger right who are digital natives
and the church speaks about these two
groups of of digital migrants and
digital natives um but for digital
natives as Edmond was saying this is
this is everything they know. Um, and
it's not like you can opt in or opt out.
It's just part of the culture. It's part
of where we are. Um, so good things
about the concept of a digital continent
is the idea of being missionaries of
knowing that we are going into a foreign
place to bring a go the gospel message a
message of of hope and and and life that
people need to hear. Um, so that's super
helpful. The digital culture um language
helps us understand that that is not
something that we can avoid but this is
where we're immersed and this is what
people are experiencing is part of their
ecosystem their ecology uh that they are
part of. So so that's that's that's a
more nuance uh concept where regardless
on your use of technology you could be a
heavy user or not um in terms of digital
tools you're still part of this new
digital culture. Um you know good news
is that the the gospel the good news are
truly good news and and this is what
people desire and and and and crave. Um
I find it very interesting you know you
see all the all the data uh from this
year in terms of the interest in the
Catholic faith you know that that is
been registered in Google searches and
so forth. Um it it coincides with these
new digital revolution connected to
artificial intelligence. So, so we see
we see two things happening here. We see
that increase in in curiosity for for
the phase uh and then we see a world
that is becoming more and more
technologically complex and advanced.
So, so we see the two things happening.
I don't think it's a coincidence. I
think it's it's connected. Right. I I
think as people are more and more part
of this digital culture, um there is a
desire for true encounter with with God
and and and a true understanding of what
human human um um what we are as humans.
So I I see the two of them very much
connected. So for me this is a a
springtime evangelization. This is the
continuation of second Vatican council
and all those promises you know. So 50
plus years after, you know, I think this
is a time where we're going to see a lot
of opportunity um in the church because
of these technological changes and what
they bring to our culture and the
questions that they pose.
>> Um how do you see AI helping parishes um
serve people better? Well, I mean, I
think part of the problem right now is
that we're not seeing a lot of parishes
using AI, but I think um you know, one
of the really uh one of the strengths of
AI is its ability to take lots of
information and um synthesize it,
organize it, things like that. So, um I
think what the first thing I come to, um
when I'm talking to someone who's not
super familiar with AI, but is in
ministry is uh not what they would
expect. They would expect often people
go and try to use AI and they just type
in like write my email for me or
something like that. There's so many
other tools that can take information.
For example, Notebook LM is one that I
refer to a lot because you're able to
upload lots of information. you could,
you know, 10 church documents or a bunch
of um catechetical resources and then
organize that information in interesting
ways. So, um in especially moving into
the the age of AI, um information is not
uh the the end- all beall anymore, the
the valuable thing. It's more like the
medieval times, right? It's how you
combine information, like we said at the
beginning, like to be useful to other
people. So there's lots of ways that um
yeah AI makes quick organization and
accuracy and things like that really
useful. Um I mean Amundo talks a lot
about this really shifted my entire
worldview on on just ministry in
general. Talks a lot about the
difference between like mission support
and mission direct. And so I think
there's a lot of opportunities in the
mission support category for behind the
scenes analyzing data getting more
accurate information and then also like
personalizing how someone like the
minister or um someone being ministered
to you like accesses that information
and data. So that's often the first
thing um I turn to because it's a lot
easier to kind of wrap your head around
is this like organizing processing
information in more useful ways.
>> And Edmundo and Edmond, could you guys
break down what is what is mission
support and mission direct?
>> Edmundo, go for it.
>> Yep. Um happy to do that. Um when when I
was working at the archis of Detroit, we
came up with this system or the
archbishop came up with this system of
or framework to think about the work
that we do um as a dascese, you know, as
a local church and and and we had this
uh kind of division of labor, right? We
have the mission support area and then
we have the mission direct area. Um but
mission support are all those um
um you know, for us we're departments
but functions. That's probably the best
way to think about that that are not
doing mission directly. They're not
impacting mission but they are
supporting mission or there is slowing
down mission or making mission less less
less effective. So that would be uh
areas like finance, HR, technology
um that in in
you know they are not necessarily
ministry but if done well um you can
really enhance ministry. So for mission
support areas what you want to look are
for our efficiencies right how do how
can we do these in a better way faster
way um so that we can free up resources
both monetary resources but also time to
do more mission and the mission direct
area is is is everything that we do as a
church that that is that is the mission.
So that would be Catholic schools and
the ministry that we have on teaching
children and teaching adults to um the
the work that we do you know
evangelization in the parishes all the
sacramental uh component of a parish. So
that would be the the mission direct and
in and in those um you really don't
you're not looking for for efficiencies
as much as as effectiveness. Are we are
we um doing mission in a way that is
he's accomplishing our our goal that
people know and love the lord that they
can encounter Jesus. So so you know when
we have this division you know there's
efficiencies in one side which is the
most important part of it and
effectiveness on the other side of
things um and both are connected you
need efficiency and effectiveness in
both areas but but it just allows you to
think differently about ministry. So
when I think about artificial
intelligence, it it's like a no-brainer
to incorporate artificial intelligence
in in all of the mission support um
areas on a parish or in a dascese
because you know you want to free up
resources. You want to have uh the
ability to invest those resources in
other things that that are mission
direct uh time and and and people
personnel and also um um you know uh
monetary resources. So that's a
no-brainer. When it becomes more of a
where the where people need a lot of
more wisdom and discernment is on the
mission direct. How do you incorporate
AI on the mission direct? And I think
people that that's where where there's a
lot of um uh concerns I would say from
from the local churches and you know
priests, pastors, layo ministers and lay
leaders. Um that's where where we're
trying to figure out how to do it. Um
there are there are frameworks to think
about that and we can talk about it
here. um that can move you from fear to
confidence and from fear to um hope in
in this age. But that's I think where
where the big conversation is happening
right now and where people are are
concerned about it. Um and and I think
sadly part of the problem is that people
are not talking about it openly. Um
because I think that it's more like you
know you're a AI user but but you don't
want to tell people because you're going
to be seen as as not not putting people
at the center and not having the human
flourishing and the human person at the
center. So you're kind of doing it but
but isolated instead of having learning
communities uh where we're talking about
how to do these in a way that advances
the mission of the church. I think that
there's a need for a greater
conversation and openness about how do
we use this technology for good and um
and that's you know I need to I need to
find the the exact quote but but what
stuck with me is that these are like
talents you know when we talk about the
parallel of talents that have been uh
provided you know in God's providence
have been available to us and then we
need to think about how to use them
permission so I I encourage a greater
conversation in pair settings and diosen
settings for for how you incorporate AI
on this mission direct and mission
support it should be all about
implementation like best practices I
mean companies are doing that like
that's an that's that's an easy win for
a lot of lot of parishes and if you
think of parishes you're thinking about
entities that have limited resources um
you know I love the definition of a
pastor is someone who is overwhelmed uh
understaffed um and underfunded you know
and and and that's a reality for most of
the pastors so incorporating AI and
mission support should be a given Now
the the fun conversation, the
interesting conversation is how do we
incorporate into your mission?
>> I I have sensed that feeling that um
that a lot of people are using it but
they just they don't want to say it. And
I I think that with more honesty that
would be a beautiful thing which is
obviously what we want to do with
Catholic futurist. Um but Edmund um I
think for for a lot of uh of our viewers
and and myself included I don't I don't
know that much about what goes into
organizing a parish. Everyone in the
parish boundary is a member of that
Catholic parish. Meaning that everyone
Catholic or non-atholic is is part of
that parish boundary. Which means that
that's that pastor's responsibility on
behalf of the bishop and Jesus to to
evangelize to make disciples to to give
the sacraments. Um so then the pastor
goes, "Man, there are tons and tons of
people in this parish boundary." Well,
um there are Catholics that show up for
worship and they're part of the
Christian community and hopefully they
are also involved in this task of
evangelization in the parish boundary.
But again, like um in today's day and
age, these parishes are are rather
large. Even the smallest parishes that
you could think of, it is hard for the
pastor to be available for all of his
people at all times. And so um you know
decades ago there was this you know more
formalized uh movement of formalizing
positions of volunteers who volunteer
voluntarily get involved in the mission
of that local church. And then we
started seeing the like
professionalizing of these roles as you
know this ley got more and more um
educated as like they get they get more
training they get more formalization
around that which is a a great thing. So
um you have in lots of dascese parishes
that have some level of paid staff
although um admittedly a lot of I mean
it varies widely like there are parishes
that have very few paid staff. So, um,
you know, to avoid getting too much into
like the canonical and theological
aspects of it, like what goes into the
parish is the pastor and either, you
know, paid staff or a combination of
paid staff and volunteers like
cooperating with the ley um to to
accomplish God's plan for for our
salvation in this local area. So,
there's kind of those three areas.
because you have the p the pastor, the
ley, and then the geographic location,
the mission territory. Um there there's
other things involved as well, but like
focusing on that for our conversation
here, like that's really the basic
elements that we're talking about when
we talk about this parish community. Um
and and I think most parishes don't
don't spend enough time thinking about
the people that don't show up,
especially in the US church, if we're
talking in particular about that. Um
because for so many years we had this um
assumed cultural religiousness or
assumed cultural cath catholicness. Um
and so lots of people talk about you
know people leaving the church and the
Catholic church um in in in droves. And
so there really is this uh we've we've
gone from there there's a book um from
criticism to apostolic mission. and I I
believe is the name of the the book, but
it's this idea that like we no longer
live in the in a civil we live in a
post-Christian civilization and culture.
So, there really is this pressing need
um you know, as the popes recently have
talked about this, the past couple
popes, like this need for this new
evangelization, this re-evangelization
of our parish boundaries. And so like
Amuna, I love Amuna said, you know, like
we would we would be disappointed. We'd
be embarrassed if we don't use the tools
that we need. In youth ministry circles,
this came up a lot. You know, there'd be
this kind of shame of like, well, Jesus
didn't use PowerPoint or Jesus didn't
have to use slick t-shirts or whatever.
And I remember sometimes I would just
quip like, yeah, Jesus didn't have
PowerPoint graphic design or toilet
paper. I would like to use toilet paper.
Who among us would give up toilet paper?
like it it doesn't mean that um the
things he did not use is is a normative
rule that he's imposing on us. Um, so
anyway, so that that's kind of what what
actually was really exciting for me was
being in these places that Pope Francis
and Evangeli Godium talked about. These
can be like places of great creativity
precisely because of their flexibility
and their localess and um the way that
the people there can be plugged into the
local culture and community. What
opportunities do you see that aren't
being that aren't being taken on a
practical level where you where you'll
look at a dascese or a parish and be
like okay I see the opportunities but
the staff is not using this tech or they
they're not seeing how they could make
their life easier in this way and
technology is is really built for that.
>> We need to create a a framework where
people can have in a in a safe and
productive way these conversations. So
the leadership needs to provide that
framework or that sandbox for people to
feel comfortable and safe to be able to
experiment and and be creative and and
and use these these technologies for
good. So so the question shouldn't be
how can we protect ourselves from this
technology but how do we use this
technology to facilitate human lives um
so that we can spread the gospel to
build community to witness for Christ.
So, so that's that's the type of spirit
that we should have. Not one about
distending ourselves from these uh
fearsome technology. Um Pope Francis
used that term. He says this is an
exciting technology but also a fearsome
technology. So it's okay to have that
fear but that that fear sometimes comes
from ignorance. So if we can defeat
ignorance then we have a chance to move
from from something that could be
potentially harmful to something that
could be really harnessed for good. So,
so providing a framework I think should
be the most important thing and I think
the Vatican is going to come with with a
document. I think Pope Le is working on
something that's going to help us. But,
but even if you look at at at the things
that are out there already, you can come
up with that framework. So, so using um
so Pope Leo already wrote um the the
world day communications message that is
going to be published next year in 2026
in February 24th in the feast of St.
Francis sale sales I believe. um but but
it's always published before or it's
it's made public now. So even if you
take some of that um uh message about
preserving human voices and faces and
other documents, you can start putting
together a framework that creates these
safe safe sandbox for us to creatively u
advance the mission of the church. So so
just things that come to mind that could
be part of that framework. You know um
human dignity needs to be at the center
and it's non-negotiable. So we can
evaluate a technology with simple
questions. Does this uplift human
dignity or is it diminishing it? Right?
So there's a way for us to create that
safe sandbox by asking these type of
questions. Um you know the the tools
that we're talking about with AI, they
they provide efficiency and reach but
they cannot and and can never replace um
the things that are uniquely human.
That's what uh Pope um Leo was saying,
right? empathy, ethics, moral
responsibility,
pastoral care, discernment. Those are
the things that need to remain human.
You know, another thing could be, you
know, that technology is not an idol,
right? Like that's the the the other
part that we see in the in the documents
that the church has published, right, in
antiqua, that technology can become this
false god for humanity that we can see
technology as saving everything that is
that needs to be saved in a parish or in
a diosin setting. Well, we shouldn't
have that approach. Um but we can see it
as a tool that can serve us and and it's
always serving us. We're never
technology is never the master and then
and then the goal is to facilitate uh
pastoral encounters. Um so those are
just a a few things. I think maybe
another another thing that comes to mind
in terms of creating a sandbox or a
framework is is is is what Pope Francis
would call the wisdom of the heart,
right? that machines can process data
but it takes the human heart to to
process meaning and to discern. So
discernment is something that that needs
to be kept there. So if you create that
sandbox in a diosin setting in a in a in
a conference you know setting in a in a
parish setting then people can be
encouraged to to creatively use these
technologies for good. Um, here are some
things that the other day Edmond and I
were talking about these and then we we
came up with some use cases that that
could be something that parishes could
consider. You know, I'm going to share
three that come to mind um that that I I
would think are pretty safe for for for
parishes to implement and consider in
these learning communities. So one would
be you know catechist like you know
Edmond and I have a project around the
catechism and and and and the project
project's goal is to to unlock the
wisdom and the beauty you know that that
we have in the catechism of the Catholic
church. Um so but but the reality is
that a lot of the catechist in a parish
they don't have the formation
um um that sometimes they require. Um
they have some formation but sometimes
it's not sufficient. Um, these are
volunteers who have busy lives and are
are serving out of love for the parish.
So, if we can equip them with with with
ways that they can leverage AI to
prepare their lessons, that would be a a
super helpful thing. So, teaching them
how to use AI not to write the lesson,
but to make it better to adapt some of
the materials for the age group that
they're teaching, that would be super
super helpful. So, so, so a simple thing
that they could do is just write your
lesson, right? Like usually parishes
provide um guides or curriculum for
every lesson. Write your lesson and then
and then ask chat chat GPT or or or um
other um AI tools, you know, to to with
some framework and with some context.
And that's what the pair should provide.
You know, h how do I adapt these in a in
the best way possible for an audience of
of of boys, sixth grade boys? How do I
adapt that here? um you know using this
framework can you tell me what things I
can I can do better in my lesson. So
those are just just things that you know
uh parishes cannot provide that that
personalized coaching for every
catechist in the parish uh but they can
provide that framework and they can
provide that way of using AI to help the
catechist become a better catechist that
doesn't substitute uh the the prayerful
spirit of a catechist of seeking the
Lord first. It doesn't substitute the
discernment. That person still needs to
discern and to make the decisions and it
doesn't replace the catechist because we
need the catechist teaching uh children
or teaching adults and passing down the
faith person to person. So so we're not
replacing anything. We're just elevating
and and make make um ministry better. So
that's just one example. I can I can
share others. Edund has a lot of good
examples that he can share as well.
>> Edmond before I go to next question is
is there anything you'd like to add on
that? I mean those those frameworks and
those examples I think um really
illustrate well kind of the
opportunities.
>> Yeah. I mean the only thing I can think
to add you know and Mundo share a lot of
these really practical things. I think I
think um the biggest thing I am most
excited about is that what we're seeing
in AI not just the technology and what
it's doing but what we're seeing is a
whole shift I think in in my view in our
in our collective view of the world. So
for hundreds of years now since um
really the enlightenment we've been
viewing the world across all different
subjects and domains um science,
religion, philosophy in in in the west
there's been this predominant view of
the world which is um that the world is
like a machine. It's mechanistic. It's
linear. It's cause and effect. And it's
interesting that in the church um as
well as in the sciences over the last
couple decades we've started to see the
breakdown of that. And I think you know
the like western civilization saw at the
the height of the fruit of this kind of
like materialistic reductionistic linear
view that you can just understand things
as parts and you put in this and you get
out this output and it just isn't it
just isn't sustainable. It's not it's
not um it doesn't match with reality.
And so like World War II and all of
these like fruits of this view of the
world. And so we're seeing like this
move towards more ecological ecology
systems view of the world which actually
is very Catholic. Like the human person
is only understood in relation to
others. So the thing I'm like really
excited about is this deeper um
worldview shift that AI forces us to
have because um there's this thing
called the realization gap. Jeremy from
uh Jeremy Utley from Stanford University
did this research where he found that
lots of people that used AI, there was a
big majority of people that were they
considered underperformers. So they
didn't get anything out of AI and then
they examined and surveyed the people
that were overperformers who who tended
to get more results. And the difference
between the two groups was that the
people who were underperformers viewed
AI as a tool whereas the people who were
overperformers viewed AI as a thinking
partner. And this is this really
highlights like this difference in
worldview of how you interact with
things. So for example, a parish someone
as a parish leader or pastor who's very
linear topdown type of approach to
leadership is like if I do X then Y
happens. But we know that that just
isn't the case. These are complex
organizations. These are complex
systems. And so a system you can't
control, you can only cultivate. So I
think what's really exciting, what
people are going to be forced to do more
and more is to think of the parish in
evangelization
um much less like a a machine to control
like you put in these inputs and you
should get out this thing and much more
like like in a sense a garden like you
you cultivate a garden you have to work
with a garden. It's interesting too that
with the rise of this idea which is
called complexity science with the rise
of this idea in the sciences we have the
rise of cidality in the church and one
of the big tenants of of complexity
theory is that you have to be sensing
what's going on discerning responding
and and facilitating and that sounds
much more like a cenodal church it
sounds much more like accompanyment and
so um Catholic leaders have to think of
themselves less as uh someone who
transfers the data or the content and
much more as a thinking partner with
those that we're ministering to, as
someone who mentors and accompanies and
is alongside. And it's interesting to
know that like Pope Leo in his um
address to the Catholic digital
missionaries said this um uh
specifically like it's not simply a
matter of generating content but of
creating an encounter of hearts. And so
we have to do away with this this old
model that we've been given even in our
in our schooling and our education
systems. This industrial view of man and
of society that's a machine it's linear
and it's much more systems. It's people
interacting listening and cultivating
and looking at the fruits of that. Um,
so that that's like a little bit deeper
and more nerdy answer, but I think AI
forces people to have to think in this
more holistic way about the outcomes
that they're trying to achieve. What how
do you guys see parishes kind of
adapting their approach to welcome kind
of these these people who are digitally
converted, you know, intellectually
converted through through the new media.
I find it super interesting
that um people open up with chatt and
other chatbots so much more than with
people. Um, so that's so so so for some
people that would be super scary and
like oh man like the world is ending
because someone opens up so much to a
machine instead of a person like you
know you guys may have seen that that
graphic that meme where it's like an
iceberg and and here's what I tell um my
friends here's what I tell my spouse
here's what I tell my therapist and here
is all that I tell uh Chad GPT
Um, and there there there's something
there that that that I think we should
all be reflecting.
So, if I would be a priest and if I'm
even an older priest priest that doesn't
quite understand everything about AI, I
should be very curious about that. I
should be thinking deeply about that
that that reality that that that that
that we have right now where where
especially young people are opening up
um so much with with with chat right
we've seen that the number one use is
not search is is um it's it's therapy
right that people are going to a chatbot
to to get therapy and and and therapy is
is a search for for what for
understanding ourselves and
understanding relationships.
Um, so, so that should be something to
reflect on regardless if you taught or
not AI. That should, that should, that
should really drive your curiosity and
start asking very, very important
questions why someone is so much more
open to share deeply
um there than than in in a in a context
uh where where there's human encounter
and divine encounter, right? and and
then what can we learn or what is are
these technologies providing that we are
not providing in the church and and what
comes to mind is the whole idea of
listening right I mean the the reason
why people share in chat GP yes there is
the the I'm embarrassed to talk to
someone about this thing with someone
else but it's this this idea that that
chat GPT is trained and other chatbots
to to be very empathetic and very
affirming and and and very welcoming to
your inquiry diaries and and and they
provide always positive feedback. When
you ask a question, they're trained to
do that and then they suggest things and
paths. So, so for someone that that may
not have a pastoral, you know, you know,
um training, uh you can start thinking
about why this is happening there. Why
are young people especially doing using
the technology in this way? And what can
we learn in the church and where can we
step up? Um, and also it's not terrible,
right? If someone has a very ver a
question that they don't feel
comfortable sharing with anyone else and
if we can point them to a technology
where they can ask those questions like
magisterium or or truthly or some of
these ch um, you know, tools that are
trained in in church churches teaching
and they're getting some answers. That's
not the end of the world. That's
actually a positive thing that people
are are finding a way to look for those
things and and honestly that's not that
different from what people were doing
before which is just asking Google right
for the same type of questions. So but
but but the difference between Google
and and AI is that that the way that the
machine responds is so empathetically
and is listening to you that you open
up, right? Um so I would be if I would
be a pastor is like I would be praying
and discerning and how can we become a
more listening community. How can we
create a spaces where people can ask
questions and not feel judged by them
but that we can welcome them and guide
them. How can we provide those
opportunities for that personal
encounter that leads to the divine
encounter? So for me that's a really
really important conversation to have um
in in in a in a church setting. Um, you
know, here's another thing that comes to
mind and um, you know, none of us wants
a priest to write their homalies, you
know, have Chad Gut write their homies,
right? That doesn't make sense, right?
And maybe there are some priests that
are doing it, but but but that doesn't
mean that you cannot use these tools to
to become a very better homalist, right?
If I would be a priest or a deacon, I
would be recording all my hallmies and I
would be loading them to to an AI tool
and I would be asking critical questions
about my my preaching. I would be asking
questions, you know, you know, feedback
with with some constraints and context.
I would be asking the AI tool I would be
providing the AI tool certain certain
frameworks to use. Okay, use this
homalytic framework, right? that is the
one that I was trained when I was a
seminary used these homalytic resources
and now I provide feedback to my my
preaching and I want to tell you also
that that the the constraints and the
context involve my community so I am in
a suburban parish or I'm in a rural
parish and the average beach is these
and the the you know the education level
is these and primarily you know this is
a type of uh uh this is this is my my my
community parish community and then
allow the tool to to to using these
these things and analyzing as Edman was
saying at the very early very early in
the podcast the the power to to do those
things as a as a pocket data scientist
and then provide feedback to you that
you know you're not going to do
everything that AI tells you but it's
going to it's going to make you uh think
deeply about your ministry with the hope
that in your 40s to grow as a better
homaly so that the word of God that
you're preaching uh could be done in a
more effective way and and I I just
wonder how we as Catholics can
effectively
be preserving and a more that that
Christian moral formation for these
young people as the technology is
allowing inputs from outside. we often
revert back to this thing that we
learned that's baked into our culture,
which is this um
this kind of
Protestant Reformation era view of what
evangelization and even the faith really
is that that it's an intellectual
pursuit and it's not an intellectual
pursuit and you this is why um Carninal
Ratzinger then Pope Benedict and JP2 and
all of these um influential thinkers
were moving towards this this resource
man to the sources not just because they
needed to reclaim tradition but because
they needed to reclaim a more complete
view of the human person and so we like
I love Aquinus and my my um yeah my
toistic brothers and sisters in Christ
like I I love them and I and as someone
who's a recovering
um Catholic intellectual like I had to
unlearn some of those habits of treating
the faith as intellectual pursuit and I
think In a lot of public discourse, we
sometimes because it it's it's exciting,
exhilarating,
um fun to show someone their flawed
thinking. But if if all of us were
rational, logical beings, like we
wouldn't have all the problems we have.
And it's not enough to just say, well,
people just refuse to accept the truth.
Like like it is the case that a purely
intellectual presentation of the faith
um is not sufficient, right? in CF all
the saints and theologians that that
write on this. And so um I think it's
very encouraging that um Pope Leo as an
Augustinian is is hopefully going to
continue to reclaim this. I mean I think
it's not a coincidence that Pope Francis
wrote on the human heart and this and
the divine heart like we reclaiming the
heart is really the antidote to that.
And so what that means is um being more
self-aware
and being more transparent about what um
because that's how you have authentic
communion with another person. Like
that's how you have authentic
relationship with another person is not
um you you sit down there and let me
just explain it to you, but it's two
people side by side who are looking out
at the world and making sense of it and
are not afraid to admit
>> the doubts and challenges and the
struggles and and to be more of a um
mentor might be the wrong word for us in
the English world, but like to be more
of a guide and a friend who's looking
out at all of these mountainous areas
and these muddy areas and saying, "Hey,
I've tried traversing those areas. I've
here are some paths that have helped for
me and like what do you need to to also
find Jesus Christ um today?" My final
question to both of you is uh if we look
at ahead at uh 2035,
what are healthy parishes doing? What
how do you guys hope you know they have
integrated AI and some of these emerging
technologies that we're we're starting
to see the fruits of now? Maybe
something that I would love for parishes
to to start doing not in 2030 or 2035
but 2026
would be providing more resources for
parents. You know, we're talking about
parenting uh but also just for the whole
parish on on how to how do we how to use
technology without abusing technology,
right? So, you know, the the technical
term would be media and artificial um
literacy, but um being able to provide
real practical resources for parents and
for parishioners
on on how to use and not abuse
artificial intelligence. So, that would
be something super super helpful that
that parishes should be thinking about
it. I think that would be mo one of the
most um welcomed um resources that that
a parish could could offer now like not
not in five years but now um you know
sometimes you know if you if you go to
an average parish you know you look like
here in the United States you know you
look at the the events that sometimes
parishes is sponsored and you know you
look at the parish events calendar and
then a lot of things you know are poorly
attended because they're
they're not touching the things that
people really care about. Um there are
the things that the parish is pushing to
others. So just is there's not a a match
of interest and need with offerings. So
I would say yeah like if I'm a pastor
and I'm you know watching this podcast
if I'm a lay leader lay minister I would
start to think about how could we create
these media and artificial intu
intelligence literacy resources courses
conversations for the parish now so that
we are using not abusing technology now
the question about the future you know
in in in five 10 years where do we want
um where do we want to be so for me I'm
going to start with the most hopeful
perspective because I that's how I think
about these things. Um maybe this is my
you know I was was sharing that I
started in in 1994 when I was in school
and that was my conversion and emerging
technologies were happening and I I
could see from there to now how we're
able to share the gospel in in such
creative ways around the world where
where back in the day you need to you
needed to own a media company or work
for a media company to put a message to
to to the people and and now you can't
you can't do it without that you know
anybody can can publish a message.
So I've seen that revolution from 1994
um to now and and you know what I see
ahead is is maybe three things. One is
um AI is going to bring the cost uh down
for a lot of the things that that right
now there are very expensive to do and
that's going to promote I I think the
leveraging media um and and creative
tools to do beautiful things that
communicate the gospel message in a very
effective way. So I could see that being
very important on how AI is going to
change media production and and
communications for good. Um I would love
in in five years to see all the parishes
leveraging AI for all the mission
support things from translations active
translations for all their you know
parishes that are multicultural to to
data analysis of the parish territory as
Edin was saying and understanding trends
and understanding opportunities to uh
parish ministers at every year you know
the priests deacons the late pil
ministers are getting better because
they're using AI as a thought partner
and a critical partner and and they're
getting better at their homalies and
preaching and the catechis
and being better teachers. So, so I
would love to see uh these AI tools,
agents helping helping the parish do
things better but never substituting
um the the human interaction and what's
uniquely human. Um so so so I would love
in five years to to be a church that is
confident, a church that is not afraid.
Uh a church that understands what AI is
and is not and is able to leverage and
hardness AI for good in a way that the
Lord would be proud of us of using these
resources that he's allowed us to have
at this time and this age and that we're
using it so that more people would come
to know and love him.
>> And Edmond, what what about for you?
Yeah, I I man I love doing this with
Admuno because it's nice. I can I can
kind of give uh maybe a a diff like a I
don't know maybe like a different take
that I wouldn't I wouldn't have given
like because I I believe what Admundo is
saying but I think the only thing I
would add I think I have like a holy
well I hope it's holy but I think I have
a particular type of um kind of
frustration with the church. So, I think
I want to paint a little bit more of a
cautionary like like uh picture that you
know the internet like I think we're
going to see something very similar to
what happened with the internet where
we're going to have similar patterns but
just heightened like intensified and
it's going to happen much quicker and
it's going to be more intense. So, um
the internet democratized information.
The internet in some ways started
decentralizing leadership and authority
and these things happen really fast. you
see this like boom in, you know, moms
and, you know, stay, you know, stay at
home parents and like college kids
starting ministries and aposttoates and
these things and the parishes like the
hearing of parishes during COVID that
didn't have a list of any of their
parishioners email addresses was really
disheartening and and and things like
that, parishes like that, it was it was
a very negative, you know, effect. Like
it it wasn't great. Um, but I think
what's really concerning is that as we
move into this AI world, those types of
mistakes are are going to be h have more
dire consequences and it's going to be
quicker. So there's uh two two ideas
like we're used to this idea of bell
curves that you know more or less
there's going to be a big group of
people that have about average
experience of things whether it's
resources or experiences time or
information but with AI we're having
more of what's called these like power
laws where you have lots and lots of
people that don't have much and then a
small small percentage that have a lot.
So if you think back to like feudal
society where you had a small small 1%
of the population had access to
resources and riches and all of this and
then everyone else had a much much
different experience. Like I think in in
in my hopeful view of the future is that
Catholic leaders, parish ministers,
pastors don't see this as just a
gimmicky tech fad, but see this as what
it is, which is a revolution of society
and the way we think and act and talk
that forces us to be
on the cutting edge of this. like we
have to be using these things or at
least like thinking about how to use
this these technologies. And um you know
as Pope Leo said in that same address he
said um today we find ourselves in a new
culture deeply characterized and formed
by technology and it's up to us to
ensure that this culture remains human.
So I think um what I hope to see is that
we understand that this is a really
really pressing time for the church to
get involved in this technological
revolution. um like we can't sit on the
sidelines and all the things Edmundo
said is like I believe 100% that we are
are given this huge opportunity to bring
the church's wisdom hope and and
confidence into these spaces but we have
to be involved in it and we it we have
to be involved in it yesterday and it's
exciting to be involved in it and there
is hope there um but I just really hope
by 2030 um we're seeing a new shift like
we're seeing something we didn't see at
the dawn on of the internet age like
we're seeing a different response and
reaction from Catholics everywhere.
>> Edmmond, thank you so much so much for
that. Um Edmundo and Edmund, I'm very
grateful for your time this morning. It
has been a fascinating and you know just
incredible conversation. I'm very
grateful for for for you joining me on
this and um um I hope to do it again
soon sometime.
>> Oh, thank you Ben. Maybe next time in
Rome, we should just go out and have a
absolutely, you know, and a good
conversation